Alexander Graham Bell Family
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers 1834-1970 (bulk 1855-1922)
MSS51268
Bell, Alexander Graham, 1847-1922
147,700 items 446 containers plus 8 oversize 183.2 linear feet 23 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Inventor and educator. Correspondence, diaries, journals, laboratory notebooks, patent records, speeches, writings, subject files, genealogical records, printed material, and other papers pertaining primarily to Bell's invention of the telephone in 1876, his contributions to the education of the deaf, and his interests in a wide range of scientific and technological fields, including aviation, eugenics, and marine engineering. The collection includes the papers of other members of the Bell, Fairchild, Grosvenor, and Hubbard families.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Names:
Bell, Alexander Graham, 1847-1922; Gallaudet, Edward Miner, 1837-1917--Correspondence; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885--Correspondence; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878--Correspondence; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968--Correspondence; Kennan, George, 1845-1924--Correspondence; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont), 1834-1906--Correspondence; Marconi, Guglielmo, marchese, 1874-1937--Correspondence; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909--Correspondence; Powell, John Wesley, 1834-1902--Correspondence; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence; Tainter, Charles Sumner, 1854-1940--Correspondence; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence; Bell family; Fairchild family; Grosvenor family; Hubbard family; Bell, Alexander Melville, 1819-1905. Papers of Alexander Melville Bell; Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard, 1859-1923. Papers of Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell; Fairchild, Marian, 1880-1962. Papers of Marian Fairchild; Hubbard, Gardiner G. (Gardiner Greene), 1822-1897. Papers of Gardiner G. Hubbard
Subjects:
Aeronautics; Deaf--Education; Elocution; Eugenics; Marine engineering; Presidents--United States; Science; Speech--Physiological aspects; Technology; Telephone--History
Occupations:
Educators; Inventors
Administrative Information
Provenance:
The papers of the Alexander Graham Bell family were given to the Library of Congress between 1947 and 1984. The main body of papers was deeded to the Library by the Bell family in 1975. Additional items were transferred from various sources in 1977. Mabel H. Grosvenor deposited material in 1976 and 1977. Additional material was purchased in 1998.
Transfers:
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographic prints, negatives, and other pictorial material have been transferred to the
Gilbert H. Grosvenor Collection of Photographs of the Alexander Graham Bell Family
in the Prints and Photographs Division. Cartographic material has been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. Music compositions have been transferred to the Music Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers.
Microfilm:
A microfilm edition of many of Bell's scientific notebooks is available on twenty-two reels Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. A microfilm edition of “The Tongue” by Alexander Bell (1790-1865) is available on one reel. The microfilm consists of a negative copy and is housed in the Photoduplication Service.
Electronic Format:
Selected items from the papers of the Alexander Graham Bell family are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/bellhtml/ and may also be viewed via links provided in the container list of this register.
Biographical Notes
Alexander Graham Bell
Date Event
1847, Mar. 3 Born, Edinburgh, Scotland
1868-1870 Attended University College, London, England
1870 Emigrated with his parents to Canada
1871-1878 Instructed teachers in the use of visible speech in a number of educational institutions in the Boston, Mass., area
1873-1876 In charge of the education of a deaf child, George Sanders Engaged in experiments leading to the invention of a phonautograph, a multiple telegraph, and an electric speaking telegraph or telephone
1876, Mar. 10 Bell's telephone transmitted its first intelligible complete sentence
1877 Married Mabel Gardiner Hubbard
1880 Received the Volta Prize and established the Volta Laboratory, Washington, D.C.
1883 Established the publication Science in cooperation with Gardiner G. Hubbard
1891 Began experiments to develop motor-powered heavier-than-air craft
1898 Began experiments which led to the development of tetrahedral kites
1898-1903 President, National Geographic Society
1898-1922 Regent, Smithsonian Institution
1907 Founded the Aerial Experiment Association
1908 Began development of the hydrodrome (hydrofoil)
1922, Aug. 2 Died, Beinn Bhreagh, near Baddeck, Nova Scotia, Canada
Alexander Melville Bell
Date Event
1819, Mar. 1 Born, Edinburgh, Scotland
1843-1865 Teacher of elocution
1844 Married Eliza Grace Symonds (died 1897)
1849 Published
A New Elucidation of the Principles of Speech and Elocution (Edinburgh: the author. 311 pp.)
1867 Published
Visible Speech: The Science of Universal Alphabetics (London: Simpkin, Marshall & Co. 126 pp.)
1868 Lectured in Canada and the United States
1870 Emigrated to Brantford, Ontario, Canada, where he became professor of elocution at Queens College, Kingston
1881 Moved to the United States
1885 Elected fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science
1898 Married Harriet Guess Shibley
1905, Aug. 7 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Alexander Graham Bell Family Papers span the years 1834-1970, with the bulk of the material concentrated during the period 1855-1922. They include correspondence, diaries, journals, speeches, publications, and scientific notebooks of Alexander Graham Bell, his wife, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell, and their forebears and descendants, members principally of the Bell,; Hubbard,; Grosvenor, and Symonds families. They document Bell's varied activities throughout his entire career. Although the bulk of the items pertains to the invention of the telephone in 1876, Bell's contributions to the education of the deaf and his scientific and technological interests in a wide range of subjects are also amply represented, including eugenics, marine engineering, and aviation.
Among the scientific material in the papers is a group of notebooks in which Bell recorded his daily experiments and observations, including the entry for March 10, 1876: "I then shouted into M[outhpiece] the following sentence: 'Mr. Watson - come here - I want to see you.' To my delight he came and declared that he had heard and understood what I said."
Although much of Bell's voluminous correspondence is contained in the General Correspondence series, an even larger part is included in a Subject File. Among the many people with whom Bell corresponded are Edward M. Gallaudet,; Joseph Henry,; Helen Keller,; George Kennan,; Samuel P. Langley,; Guglielmo Marconi,; Simon Newcomb,; John Wesley Powell,; Charles Sumner Tainter, and several presidents of the United States, including Ulysses S. Grant,; Theodore Roosevelt,; William H. Taft, and Woodrow Wilson.
The Family Papers series includes papers of Alexander Graham Bell's father, Alexander Melville Bell, a leader in the field of vocal physiology and elocution, and Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell's father, Gardiner Greene Hubbard, one of the founders of the telephone industry and the first president of the National Geographic Society. There is also a group of letters exchanged between Alexander Graham and Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell, 1875-1921. The Family Papers extend to many of Bell's descendants, including members of the Fairchild and Grosvenor families.
Additions made to the collection in 1981 and 1998 include correspondence and related papers of the Genealogical Record Office founded by Bell to study the impact of heredity on longevity. Also included are docket books of United States and British patents, published volumes of the American Annals of the Deaf, some of which were annotated by Alexander Graham Bell, correspondence of Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell and her daughter, Marian Fairchild, scrapbooks, and court proceedings of Bell patent litigation.
Related Material
The
Grosvenor Family Papers
in this division include material related to Alexander Graham Bell and his family.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in twelve series:
Journals and Diaries, 1867-1910
Family Papers, 1834-1972, n.d.
General Correspondence, 1870-1922, n.d.
Subject File, 1845-1939, n.d.
Beinn Bhreagh Recorder, 1909-1922
Scientific Notebooks, 1879-1922, n.d.
Article and Book File, 1901-1904, n.d.
Speeches and Interviews File, 1876-1922, n.d.
Miscellany, 1865-1974
Additions, 1847-1954, n.d.
Oversize, 1872-1956, n.d.
Microfilm, 1861-1922
Container List
- Journals and Diaries, 1867-1910 (Box 1)
  Holograph or typescript copies of journals and diaries kept by Alexander Graham Bell.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Journals, 1877, 1898, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1867, 1875, 1888
- Family Papers, 1834-1972, n.d. (Box 1-101)
  Correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, books, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of the family member and thereunder by type of material.
  - Bell, Aileen Adine (Box 1)
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander (1790-1865)
    - General correspondence
      - Fuller, Sarah
    - Miscellany
  - Bell, Alexander (1790-1865)
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Melville
    - General correspondence, A-Z
    - Book file
      - The New Testament of Our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ
      - The Practical Elocutionist
    - Lecture file
      - "The Commonwealth"
      - "On Humbug" (Box 2)
      - "On the Character and Tragedy of Macbeth"
      - "Public Speaking"
      - "Stammering"
      - Lecture and teaching announcements
    - Playscript file
      - Play of Douglas
    - Poetry file
      - "The Tongue" See also Microfilm III
    - Poems, plays, and articles
    - Thesis on public reading and poetry
    - Miscellany (Box 3)
      - Biographical material
      - Certificates
      - "Herbatium"
  - Bell, Alexander Melville
    - Journals, 1840, 1850, 1885, n.d.
    - Diaries, 1851, 1904
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
        - 1862-1866
        - 1867-1873, (8 folders) See also Oversize (Box 4)
        - 1874-1876, (7 folders) (Box 5)
        - 1877-1882, (9 folders) (Box 6)
        - 1883-1905, n.d., (7 folders) See also Oversize (Box 7)
      - Bell, Alexander (1790-1865)
      - Bell, Caroline Ottoway ("Carrie")
      - Bell, Charles James
      - Bell, Chichester Alexander
      - Bell, David Charles
      - Bell, Edward Charles
      - Bell, Eliza Symonds
      - Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard
      - Bell, Melville James (Box 8)
      - Grosvenor, Elsie Bell
      - Grosvenor, Gilbert Hovey
      - Home, Sophie C.
      - Hubbard, Gardiner Greene
      - Kerr, Lily F.
      - Symonds, Charles H.
      - Symonds, James W.
      - Symonds, Mary
    - General correspondence
      - Letterbook, 1853-1857
      - Adams, Charles
      - Adler, Cyrus
      - Allen, Hugh P.
      - Aytoun, William G.
      - Berliner, Emile
      - Blackie, John Stuart
      - Bonaparte, Louis Lucien
      - Brewster, David For additional material see Containers 12-14, Visible speech
      - Browning, Robert
      - Coats, George J.
      - Coats, Margaret
      - Coats, Thomas
      - Donaldson, James, Sir
      - Edward VII, king of Great Britain
      - Ellis, Alexander John For additional material see Container 82, Biography of Alexander Graham Bell, and Containers 201-203, Visible speech
      - Findlater, Andrew
      - Fuller, Sarah
      - Gilman, Daniel C.
      - Hale, Horatio
      - Hill, David J.
      - Hill, Thomas
      - Hitz, John
      - Holmes, Oliver Wendell (1809-1894) For additional material see Container 64, Death of Alexander Graham Bell, and Container 133, Peirce, Benjamin
      - King, Dexter S.
      - Lytton, Edward Bulwer Lytton, Baron
      - McCurdy, Arthur W.
      - Müller, F. Max
      - Murchison, Roderick I.
      - Palmerston, Henry J.
      - Pitman, Isaac
      - Porter, Samuel
      - Porter, Sarah
      - Scudder, Samuel H. For additional material see Container 271, Science
      - Smith, Goldwin
      - Spofford, Ainsworth Rand For additional material see Container 10, Literary Society of Washington
      - Sweet, Henry
      - Victoria, Queen of Great Britain
      - Warren, William F. For additional material see Container 64, Death of Alexander Graham Bell, and Container 133, Peirce, Benjamin
      - Williams, Charles, Jr. (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, A-W, and unidentified, (3 folders)
    - Subject file
      - Bell Home for Children, Colonial Beach, Va.
      - Biographical information, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - Confederate States of America
      - Congregational Church, Cambridge, Mass.
      - Death of Alexander Melville Bell, scrapbook
      - Elocution
      - Index Rerum: or, Index of Subjects...
      - Lawsuit, testimony
      - Line writing
      - Literary Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
      - Phrenological reading (Box 11)
      - Religion
      - Shorthand
      - Speech impediments
      - Telephone, (3 folders)
      - Visible speech, (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
      - Wedding anniversary, fiftieth
      - World English
    - Article file
      - "Address in Elocution and Popular Oratory"
      - "An Alphabet of Orators"
      - "Articulation"
      - "A Chapter on Impediments"
      - "Common Sense in Its Relations to Homeopathy and Allopathy"
      - "Defects and Peculiarities of Speech"
      - "Elliptical Steno-Phonography" (Box 15)
      - "Elocution"
      - "English Line Writing"
      - "English Reporting Steno-Phonography"
      - "English Vernacular and Orthoepic Line-Writing"
      - "English Visible Speech and Its Typography Elucidated"
      - "The Fundamentals of Elocution"
      - "Hand-Book of World English"
      - "How to Speak All Languages"
      - "Ideography"
      - "Mid-Ocean Telegraph, Meteorological and Relief Station"
      - "National Education"
      - "Note on Syllabic Consonants"
      - "Notes from a Clergyman's Manuscript"
      - "On Death"
      - "On Stammering"
      - "On Teaching Reading in Public School"
      - "On the Scheme of Amended Orthography"
      - "On Visible Speech"
      - "Parliament and the Social Order"
      - "Phonetic Syllabication"
      - "Phonetics"
      - "Public Speaking and Speakers" (Box 16)
      - "Sermon Reading and Memoriter Delivery"
      - "The Sounds of R"
      - "Stories and Rhymes in Melville Bell Symbols"
      - "Eliza Grace Symonds"
      - "Upon the Art of Describing Observations"
      - "What Am I?"
    - Book file
      - Advertisements and reviews
      - Bell's Standard Elocutionist
      - Elocution
      - The Emphasized Liturgy
      - English Visible Speech in Twelve Lessons (Box 17)
      - Englishe Sichtbare-Sprache in Zwölf Lektionen
      - Essays and Postscripts on Elocution
      - Expressive Reading and Gesture
      - Facial Speech Reading and Articulation Teaching
      - The Faults of Speech
      - Language of the Passions
      - List of publications
      - Observations on Speech
      - Principles of Elocution
      - Principles of Speech and Dictionary of Sounds (Box 18)
      - The Principles of Speech, Orthoepy and Elocution
      - Pronunzia Inglese Visible Insegnata In Dodici Lezioni
      - Science of Speech
      - Sounds and Their Relations
      - Speech Reading and Articulation Teaching
      - Universal Line-Writing and Steno-Phonography
      - University Lectures on Phonetics
      - Visible Speech and Vocal Physiology
      - Visible Speech Reader
      - Visible Speech: The Science of Universal Alphabetics (Box 19)
      - What Is to Be Done with Our Convicts
      - Word Play
      - World English: The Universal Language
    - Lecture file
      - "Acting and Oratory"
      - "Alfred Tennyson"
      - "The Art of Delivery"
      - "The Bloomsbury Christening"
      - "The Cultivation of the Voice"
      - "Dickens"
      - "The Elements of Language and Dialects"
      - "Elocution"
      - "Imitation and Imitators"
      - "Julius Caesar"
      - "King Lear" (Box 20)
      - "The Lady of the Lake"
      - "Lalla Rookh"
      - "Lesson to a Shadow-Class of Students"
      - "Literal Shorthand or Neography"
      - "Macaulay"
      - "Macbeth"
      - "The Merchant of Venice"
      - "The Merry Wives of Windsor"
      - "On Dialects"
      - "Othello"
      - "Robert Burns"
      - "Romeo and Juliet"
      - "Sir Walter Scott"
      - "The Tempest"
      - "Thomas Hood"
      - "The Vices of Speech"
      - Advertisements, (3 vols.) See also Oversize (Box 21)
    - Playscript file (Box 22)
      - The Beggar's Marriage Gift
      - Colour
      - Getting up a Company
      - The Regent
      - Three Generations
      - Untitled plays
    - Poetry file
      - Miscellaneous poems, (2 folders)
    - Readings file and condensations by Bell of writings of well-known authors and poets, (5 folders); (2 folders) (Box 23, Box 24)
    - Speech file
      - By title
        - "Address to the National Association of Elocutionists"
        - Lowell Institute, Boston, Mass., lecture series
        - "Notations in Elocutionary Teachings"
        - "Note on Syllabic Consonants"
        - "On the Use of Notations in Elocutionary Teaching"
        - "Oratory"
        - "The Science of Universal Alphabetics"
        - "Speech Tones"
        - "The Telephone"
        - "What Speech Is"
      - By date
        - 1861, Mar. 20
        - 1881, 1893-1899, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 25)
    - Writings by persons other than Alexander Melville Bell
    - Miscellany
      - Bills and receipts
      - Book of accounts
      - Books, catalog
      - Certificates and awards
      - Estate of Alexander Melville Bell
      - Financial papers, (2 folders)
      - Memorials
      - Miscellany (Box 26)
      - Notebooks, (3 folders)
      - Passports
      - Printed matter, (2 folders)
      - Scrapbook
  - Bell, Archibald (Box 27)
  - Bell, Caroline Ottoway (Carrie)
  - Bell, Charles James
  - Bell, Chichester Alexander
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
    - Article file
    - Subject file
      - Scientific experiments, 1881-1884, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany
  - Bell, David Charles
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
    - General correspondence, A-Z
    - Miscellany
      - List of family birthdays, printed matter, etc.
      - Obituary, 1902
  - Bell, Edward Charles
  - Bell, Eliza Symonds
    - Journals
      - 1850
      - 1853-1854, 1856, 1860, 1862, 1884, (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - Diary, ca. 1889
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
        - 1865-1873, (4 folders)
        - 1874-1877, (8 folders) (Box 29)
        - 1878-1896, n.d, (10 folders) (Box 30)
      - Bell, Alexander Melville
      - Bell, Caroline Ottoway ("Carrie")
      - Bell, Lewis K.
      - Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard
        - 1875-1878, (2 folders)
        - 1879-1896, (6 folders) (Box 31)
      - Bell, Melville James
      - Grosvenor, Elsie Bell
      - Home, Sophie C.
      - Kennedy, Gracie Bell
      - Leplastrier, Frances Symonds
      - Symonds, Charles H.
      - Symonds, Edith
      - Symonds, Edward S., 1875-1896, (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - Symonds, H. H.
      - Symonds, Hetty J.
      - Symonds, James W.
      - Symonds, Katie I.
      - Symonds, Louisa Frankland
      - Symonds, Mary E.
      - Symonds, Stanley
      - Unidentified family members
    - General correspondence
      - Fuller, Sarah, (2 folders)
      - Hitz, John
      - McCurdy, Arthur W.
      - Miscellaneous, A-Z
      - Smith, I.
      - Smith, Maggie
    - Article file
      - "The Anti-Dandy Society"
      - "Description of Anatomical Drawings"
      - Scottish Highlands
    - Playscript file (Box 33)
    - Poetry file
      - "Flowers in Heaven"
    - Miscellany
      - Account book
      - Notebooks
      - Portrait information
      - Scrapbook
      - Sketches
      - Will and estate papers (Box 34)
  - Bell, Elizabeth Coville
  - Bell, Ellen
  - Bell, Gardiner H.
  - Bell, George T.
  - Bell, Grace Hubbard
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
      - Hubbard, Gertrude McCurdy
  - Bell, H. G.
  - Bell, Harriet Shibley
  - Bell, Helen Adine
  - Bell, Lewis K.
  - Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard
    - Diaries
      - 1870-1873, (6 folders)
      - 1877, 1879-1880, (3 folders) (Box 35)
      - 1883-1888, 1895-1896, (9 folders) (Box 36)
      - 1905-1907, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - Letterbooks, 1902, 1910-1911
    - Family correspondence
      - Bell, Aileen Adine
      - Bell, Alexander Graham
        - 1875, (2 folders)
        - 1875-1876, (10 folders) (Box 38)
        - 1877-1879, (8 folders) (Box 39)
        - 1879-1883, (9 folders) (Box 40)
        - 1884-1891, (10 folders) (Box 41)
        - 1891-1892, (9 folders) (Box 42)
        - 1892-1895, (8 folders) (Box 43)
        - 1895-1896, (9 folders) See also Oversize (Box 44)
        - 1896-1898, (8 folders) (Box 45)
        - 1899-1901, (9 folders) (Box 46)
        - 1901-1902, (8 folders) (Box 47)
        - 1903-1907, (9 folders) (Box 48)
        - 1908-1911, (8 folders) (Box 49)
        - 1912-1921, n.d., (9 folders) (Box 50)
      - Bell, Alexander Melville (Box 51)
      - Bell, Caroline Ottoway ("Carrie")
      - Bell, Charles James
      - Bell, Chichester Alexander
      - Bell, Eliza Symonds, (2 folders)
      - Bell, Ellen
      - Bell, Grace Hubbard
      - Bell, Harriet G.
      - Blatchford, Mary
      - Ely, Auguste E. G.
      - Fairchild, David
      - Fairchild, Marian ("Daisy"), (3 folders)
      - Greene, Gardiner (Box 52)
      - Grossman, Gertrude Hubbard
      - Grosvenor, Edwin A.
      - Grosvenor, Edwin Prescott
      - Grosvenor, Elsie Bell, (2 folders)
      - Grosvenor, Gertrude
      - Grosvenor, Gertrude H. (Mrs. Asa Grosvenor)
      - Grosvenor, Gilbert Hovey, (2 folders)
      - Grosvenor, Lilian Waters
      - Grosvenor, Mabel H.
      - Grosvenor, Melville Bell
      - Grosvenor, Thelma
      - Home, Douglas R.
      - Home, Richard H.
      - Home, Sophie C.
      - Hubbard, Charles Eustis
      - Hubbard, F. Tracy
      - Hubbard, Florence M.
      - Hubbard, Gardiner Greene
        - 1870-1889, (10 folders)
        - 1891-1897, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 53)
      - Hubbard, Gertrude McCurdy
        - 1871-1879, (4 folders)
        - 1880-1905, (9 folders) (Box 54)
        - 1906-1909, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 55)
      - Hubbard, Grace (Box 56)
      - Hubbard, Harry M.
      - Hubbard, James M.
      - Hubbard, John P.
      - Hubbard, Paul M.
      - Hubbard, Roberta
      - Hubbard, Samuel
      - Hubbard, Sophie
      - Hubbard, Susan
      - Kerr, James
      - Marsh, E. J.
      - Marsh, Roberta
      - Marsh, Sara L.
      - Marsh, Sarah Griswold See also Container 58, Wagner, Sarah Griswold
      - McCurdy, Caroline
        - 1870-1894, (6 folders)
        - 1895-1920, (8 folders) (Box 57)
        - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 58)
      - McCurdy, George W.
      - McCurdy, Georgianna
      - McCurdy, Gertrude Mercer Lee (grandmother of Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell)
      - McCurdy, John A. D.
      - McCurdy, Mabel B.
      - McCurdy, Robert H. (grandfather of Mabel Gardiner Hubbard Bell)